<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="overview"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	
	<title>Spring Social Facebook Overview</title>

	<section id="overview-introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>

		<para>
			The Spring Social Facebook project is an extension to <ulink url="http://www.springframework.org/spring-social">Spring Social</ulink> that enables integration with Facebook.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			With over 700 million users (and growing), <ulink url="http://www.facebook.com">Facebook</ulink> is the largest online social network.
			While bringing together friends and family, Facebook also offers a rich platform on which to develop applications.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Spring Social Facebook enables integration with Facebook with <classname>FacebookConnectionFactory</classname>, a connection factory that can be plugged into Spring Social's service provider connection framework, and with an API binding to Facebook's REST API.
		</para>
		
	</section>

	<section id="overview-howtoget">
		<title>How to get</title>

		<para>
			The following Maven dependency will add Spring Social Facebook to your project:
		</para>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<dependency>
  <groupId>org.springframework.social</groupId>
  <artifactId>spring-social-facebook</artifactId>
  <version>${org.springframework.social-facebook-version}</version>
</dependency>]]>
		</programlisting>

		<para>
			As an extension to Spring Social, Spring Social Facebook depends on Spring Social. 
			Spring Social's core module will be transitively resolved from the Spring Social Facebook dependency.
			If you'll be using Spring Social's web module, you'll need to add that dependency yourself:
		</para>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<dependency>
  <groupId>org.springframework.social</groupId>
  <artifactId>spring-social-web</artifactId>
  <version>${org.springframework.social-version}</version>
</dependency>]]>
		</programlisting>

		<para>
			Note that Spring Social Facebook may release on a different schedule than Spring Social.
			Consequently, Spring Social's version may differ from that of Spring Social Facebook.
		</para>

		<para>
			Consult <ulink url="http://docs.spring.io/spring-social/docs/1.0.x/reference/html/overview.html#overview-howtoget">Spring Social's reference documentation</ulink> for more information on Spring Social dependencies.
		</para>
	</section>
	
</chapter>
